Abandoned artificial satellites.
Tanks jettisoned from shuttles.
（ナレーション）
使い捨てられた人工衛星
シャトルが切り離したタンク
Refuse generated during
space station construction.
ステーション建造時に出た廃棄物
This vast amount of junk floating in space,
space debris, is a very serious threat.
宇宙に浮かぶ たくさんのゴミ
スペースデブリは
実は とても危険な存在です
This is a story of 2075, a time in which
this space garbage has become a problem.
2075年―
これは 宇宙のゴミが
問題になった時代の物語
♪～
♪そして人は時空(とき)を
越えた夢を見る
Soshite hito wa toki wo koeta yume wo miru
And people dream dreams that transcend time.
♪静寂の宇宙(うみ)に抱かれて
seijyaku no umi ni idakarete
Held in the depths of the sea.
♪鳥や雲を見上げては
tori ya kumo wo miagete wa
As they look up at the stars and clouds.
♪儚(はかな)い生命(いのち)燃やした
hakanai inochi moyashita ikusen no asa ni
It set their ephemeral souls on fire on a thousand mornings.
♪幾千の朝に
♪光が向かう場所へ
hikari ga mukau basho he habataku darou
I bet they're taking right to where the light is headed.
♪羽ばたくだろう
daichi wo ima tori yoku kette
Now kickoff from the ground like a bird.
♪願いを放つ時は今
hatenaki yume wo noseta furontia he
Off into the frontier that is carrying boundless dreams.
♪果てなき夢を乗せた
♪フロンティアへ
♪遠く遠く Dive in the Sky
tooku tooku dive in the sky
Farther and farther dive in the sky.
Phase 3
Return Trajectory
（タナベ）うーん… 先輩
ここ どう書けばいいんですか？
Senpai, what should I write here?
（ハチマキ）
なんで俺に聞くんだよ
What are you
asking me for?
始末書なら 先輩がいちばん
たくさん書いてるからって皆さんが
Everybody says that you've sent in more written
apologies than anyone else, so I thought...
（ハチマキ）んあ？ 皆さん？
They did, huh?
Senpai...
先輩
分かった
じゃ 言うとおりに書けよ
Yeah, fine.
Write down what I say.
Sure.
はい
"Sorry about nearly screwing up
your flight."
“定期便の邪魔をして悪かったな”
"But we might end up doing it again,
so bear with us, okay?"
“けど また やらかしちまうかも
しれないから よろしくな”
Senpai, you'll never be popular
with the girls with that attitude.
先輩 そんなんじゃ
女の子にモテませんよ
Nobody asked you. The girls with
an eye for quality are lookin'.
余計なお世話だ
見てる女は ちゃんと見てるんだよ
They go, "I've had my eye
on you for ages!"
ずっと あなたを見てました
"I've worried myself sick with you
working such a dangerous job!"
危険な仕事をするあなたのことが
心配でたまらないんです… ってな
マイ宇宙船のときも
そうでしたけど―
It was like this during the
"my spaceship" incident, too.
どうして
そう 漫画みたいな発想しか―
Why are all of your fantasies like
something out of a comic book?
出てこないんですか？
お前なあ 新入りのくせに
少しは先輩を…
Look here, rookie! How about showing
your senpai a little...
- Hello there, Hoshino Hachirota-san!
お前なあ 新入りのくせに
少しは先輩を…
（女性）こんにちは
星野(ほしの)八郎太(はちろうた)さん
あっ…
Um... And you are...?
（ハチマキ）
えーっと どちらさまでしょうか？
（女性）
ずーっと見ていたわ あなたのこと
I've had my eye on you
for ages.
えっ…
危険な仕事をしている
あなたのことが―
I worry myself sick with you
working such a dangerous job.
心配でたまらないの
ああ…
（女性）あなたのこと もっと
いろいろと教えてほしいの
There are so many things I want
you to tell me about yourself.
S-Sure, if there's anything
I can do to help...
（ハチマキ）はい 僕で よければ…
Then, would you mind
signing this?
じゃあ これにサインして！
（ハチマキ）あ？
You mustn't let your guard down
just because you're young!
（女性）
若いからって 安心してちゃ駄目よ
Outer space
is full of dangers!
宇宙には危険がいっぱい
いざというときの
コズミック生命保険 ね？
Cosmic Life Insurance is there
for life's little surprises. Right?
Insurance?
保険？
（ハチマキ）くっ 出てけーっ！
GET OUT!
（女性）もう
恥ずかしがり屋さんなんだから～
Oh, I love how you play
hard to get!
保険の勧誘って
宇宙にもあるんですね
Wow, there's insurance solicitation
even in space...
Especially at this time
of year.
（フィー）特に この時期はね
この時期？
This time of year?
（保険外交員１）
事故は もちろん―
Accidents are covered, naturally, as are
all of your family's medical expenses!
ご家族の病気も
全てカバーするんですよ
I already have insurance.
（課長）
保険なら もう 入ってるから
That's not true
at all, sir!
（保険外交員２）
いえいえ それが大間違い
私どもの保険は
従来のものとは異なるタイプでして
My company's insurance is unlike
any insurance that's come before!
（ラビィ）そう言って
毎年 同じやつじゃないか
- Can I have one?
They say that, but it's the same old thing every year.
- Have them all if you like.
- In that case...
Hachi, this one's yours.
さあ ハチ これ お前の分
たく… 面倒くせえなあ
Man, what a pain
in the ass...
Just use the one I turned in
last year.
去年のやつ そのまま使ってくれよ
Company policy is that you
make a new one every year.
毎年 新しく書くのが
決まりなんだから
はい タナベ君も
And one for you, Tanabe-kun.
何ですか？ これ
What's this for?
遺言状だよ
（タナベ）えっ？
Your last will
and testament.
書いたら この封筒に入れて
シール 貼って提出
Once you've written it, put it in
the envelope, seal it, and turn it in.
締め切りは 今週中だから
The deadline is the end
of the week, okay?
遺言状？
Last will
and testament?
ちょっ それって
死ぬとき書く あれですよね？
W-Wait, you mean that thing
you write for when you die?!
そうだよ
That's right.
In this job, there's no telling
when you might die.
この仕事は
いつ死ぬか分かんねえからな
（フィー）
実際 この間も死にかけたしね
Yeah, you almost died
a while back, remember?
あっ…
（タナベ）そんな…
You're kidding...
That's right! Life insurance is for those
"You're kidding" times in life.
（保険外交員１）そうなんですよ
そんな もしものための生命保険
（保険外交員２）備えて安心―
Preparedness is peace of mind.
Satisfaction once you're signed up.
入って満足
税金も お安くなりますし
And it lowers
your tax bill, too.
Um, what should I do
about insurance?
あの… 保険って どうすれば
好きにしたら
遺言状の時期って―
It's your call.
"Will Season" is when they
make their money,
so I'm sure they'll be happy
to tell you all about it.
彼らも稼ぎ時だから
いっぱい教えてもらえるしね
いい機会だから 死後のこととか
いろいろ考えてみてもいいかもよ
It's also a good opportunity to give some thought
to what'll happen after you die
and stuff like that.
（タナベ）はあ
（保険外交員１）
保険屋のクズだ クズ
You give insurance salesmen
a bad name!
（係員）保険会社の方々は
必ず受け付けを済ませてください
All insurance company personnel,
please make sure to register with reception.
許可証は テクノーラ社の
管轄であるかぎりは―
Permits are valid for all one-G and zero-G blocks,
so long as they are under Technora jurisdiction.
１Ｇおよび ０Ｇブロック
全て有効です
A small premium will give you
lifelong coverage!
（保険外交員１）
わずかの掛け金で一生保障
これで老後も安心ですよ
It'll give you peace of mind
in your golden years!
You'll recoup your investment
once it reaches maturity,
（保険外交員２）
満期になれば戻ってくるんだし―
こういうのは
若いうちに入っといたほうが―
...so you get the best deal by signing up
for these things while you're still young!
何かとお得なんだから
あら あなたは どう？
Oh, and how about you,
young man?
（男性）いや 僕はベガ社なんで…
No thanks.
I'm with Vega Corp, so l...
Oh! I'll see you
next month, then!
あら じゃあ 来月よろしくね
Please, for heaven's sake!
（保険外交員１）
頼みますよ 助けると思って
My company is rated triple-A,
so choose mine!
（保険外交員２）我が社は
格付けトリプルＡですから
（保険外交員３）
３か月だけ ３か月だけでいいから
Three months! Just for three months!
I'll give you all the little gifts I have!
全部あげる この粗品
（チェンシン）えっ でも まあ
３か月ぐらいなら…
Well, if it's just three
months, maybe I could...
（保険外交員３）ありがとう！
Thank you!
く… 苦しい
C-Can't breathe...!
I'm sorry!
すいませーん
（保険外交員４）ああ 待って
Hey, wait!
（保険外交員５）
ノルマがあるのよ ノルマが
But I have a quota to meet!
（保険外交員３）ありがとう
- Thank you so much!
（ラビィ）今年も やっかいな
季節がやってきましたねえ
The most annoying season of the year
is upon us once again, isn't it, Chief?
When you listen to those agents give their spiel,
you end up signing something somehow.
（課長）
保険屋さんの説明 聞いてると―
なんか入っちゃうんだよねえ
（ラビィ）
私ら デブリ課といっても―
We're in Debris Section,
but we mostly do desk work...
デスクワークですしね
I'm about ready to retire, so I don't need
insurance that costs that much...
僕 もうすぐ 定年だからさ―
そんなに高い保険なんか
入らなくてもいいんだけど
グッドアイデアがありますよ
課長 名付けて―
I have got a great idea, Chief!
I call it...
グッドアイデアがありますよ
課長 名付けて―
（課長）あ？
..."Operation See no Evil,
Speak no Evil, Hear no Evil."
（課長）あ？
“見ざる 言わざる
聞かざる作戦”ですよ
（課長）ああ
これなら
勧誘のしようが ないでしょ？
If we do that, they can't
sell us anything, right?
Hey, that's
a good idea!
ああ そりゃ いいねえ
Isn't it, though? I was up all
last night coming up with it.
でしょ！
ゆうべ寝ないで考えましたから
（課長）
うわっ ラビィちゃん 下 下
Lavie! Look down!
Look down!
あっ 申し訳ありません
I'm so sorry!
Forget about that,
just put that back!
いいから 早く戻して
（ラビィ）あっ はい
Yes, sir!
（タナベ）“お父さん お母さん
先立つ不孝をお許しください”
"Dear Mom and Dad, please forgive the sadness
I've caused by dying before you."
うーん… “お父さんへ”
"Dear Dad. Rock music doesn't
work with funerals, so don't..."
“葬式にロックは
似合わないので”って 違う
No, that's no good...
"Write out your last will,"
they say...
遺言なんて
いきなり言われてもなあ
ん？
あっ 何？ これ
What's this?
（ハチマキ）おい
Hey.
あっ
Who said you could
look at that?
何 勝手に見てんだよ
あっ その 何ですか？ これ
I was just, uh...
What is this?
（ハチマキ）遺言
My last will.
えっ はあ？
You were told to write one, too, remember?
They said to turn it in by the end of the week.
お前も書けって言われたろ？
今週中に出せって
Your last will? Seriously?
遺言 ほんとに？
何だよ 何か文句でもあるのか？
What, you got a problem with that
or something?
But a will is supposed to have things like parting
words for parents or friends, or thanks for...
遺言って 両親や友達に
別れの言葉とか 感謝の…
（ハチマキ）ねえよ 別に
I don't have anything
to say.
あるでしょ？ お別れなんですよ
最後なんですよ？
Of course you do!
You're saying goodbye!
You're dead!
いいんだよ 何だって
死んだら 全部おしまいなんだから
It doesn't matter what I write.
Once I'm dead, it's all over for me.
That's the coldest thing I've ever heard!
何 寂しいこと
言っちゃってるんですか
If they saw a will like this, the people you
leave behind would break down in tears!
この遺言状 見たら
残された人が悲しみますよ？
You think so? I kinda think
they'd bust out laughing.
そうかなあ 笑うと思うがなあ
This is no good!
Rewrite it!
駄目です 書き直し！
ったく… なんで お前に―
Unbelievable... What did I ever do to deserve
being lectured by the likes of you?
そんなこと言われなくちゃ
ならねえんだよ
（タナベ）うっ…
（ハチマキ）フンッ！
ほら これでいいだろ？
Here.
Happy now?
うっ…
もう いいです
Oh, forget it.
（ヴァンリ）遺言状って言われても
正直 実感 湧かないなあ
All this stuff about last wills just isn't
hitting home for me, to tell you the truth.
It's not like we go out
into space all that often.
（シャポウ）私たちは そんなに
宇宙に出るわけじゃないしね
But my section does go out,
so it makes me think...
でもさ うちは
直接 外に出るから考えちゃうよ
（リュシー）
他のデブリ課の人たちは―
What are the other Debris Section
people writing in theirs?
何て書いてるの？
ほら 例のおむつ男とか
Like that diaper guy,
for instance.
（タナベ）ああ 落書き男
Oh, Sketch Boy,
you mean...
落書き？
Sketch Boy?
だって
遺言状に落書き 書いてあんのよ
The jerk drew a sketch
as his last will!
普通は 大事な人に―
Don't you normally write down heartfelt words
for the people who were important to you?
心のこもった言葉を
残すもんじゃない？
うーん 遺言なんて
結局 個人の自由でしょ
Well, in the end, a last will
is a personal thing.
でも 私は嫌だな
I still don't think
it's right.
愛だね これは
It must be love.
（タナベたち）はあ？
気になるんでしょ？
その人のこと
That person is on
your mind a lot, isn't he?
リュシーって どうして そう
色恋に結び付けようとするかな
Lucie, why are you trying
to turn this into a love affair?
私は 男女の友情って
信じないほうだから
Because I don't believe that
men and women can be "just friends."
それより 保険屋よ 保険屋
And what about all those
insurance salesmen, huh?
Yeah, that's right! I got suckered
into a married couple's plan!
そうそう 私なんて―
ご夫婦安心プランに
入らされちゃって
（シャポウ）結婚するの？
（ヴァンリ）しないよ 同僚は勘弁
You're getting married?
No, I'm not!
I don't date coworkers.
I dunno, I might.
（リュシー）私はしてもいいな
Who, that pilot?
（ヴァンリ）例のパイロット？
（リュシー）そう チェンシンさん
Yeah, Cheng-Shin-san!
（ヴァンリ）ウ～
（リュシー）ウフフッ
That's the last of our interior
maintenance work, right?
（ユーリ）内部整備は
これで おしまいですよね
（ババイヤン）ああ… ああ それと
課長のインコなんだけどさ―
Yep. Oh, and about my chief's parakeet...
Could I leave him with you again?
また 預かってもらえねえか？
（ユーリ）
マッケンローですね いいですよ
You mean MacEnroe?
Sure, no problem.
Sorry to keep pushing him
off on you.
（ババイヤン）いつも悪いな
（フィー）ユーリ
Yuri.
Yes?
（ユーリ）はい
やっぱり もう１台
フィッシュボーンを出すわ
I'm gonna go ahead and send out a second
Fishbone. There's just too much debris.
数が多すぎる
（ババイヤン）じゃ
（ユーリ）分かりました
See you.
I understand. Miss Tanabe probably can't
handle one yet, so I'll take it out.
まだ タナベさんには
無理でしょうから 私が出ます
Thanks,
that's a big help.
（フィー）
助かるわ …で 当のタナベは―
So, is our little Tanabe
still writing her last will?
まだ書いてるの？ 遺言状
ええ 随分 悩んでいるみたいですよ
Yes, she seems to be
agonizing over it.
アドバイスしましょうか
Shall I offer her
some advice?
放っといていいよ
No, leave her be.
大事なのは
何を書くかじゃなくて―
What's important isn't
what she writes, but that she learns that this
is a job that might get her killed.
死ぬかもしれない仕事だって
知っとくことだからね
（タナベ）
先輩 遺言状のことなんですけど
Senpai, about our last wills...
まだ悩んでるわけ？ お前
ああいうのは勢いだよ
What, you're still racking your brain over that?
Go with your gut with this stuff.
You gotta clear your head and start writing.
何も考えずに
ガーッと書いちまわねえと
（タナベ）
そんなわけにはいきませんよ
I can't do that.
両親や友達に何を残すのか
残せるのかって考えたら
When I start thinking about what I'll leave to my
parents and friends, or what I should leave, I...
（ハチマキ）残すってよ
Leave behind, huh?
（女性）残ってほしいのは
やっぱり お金… でしょ？
What they want you to leave
them is money. Am I right?
Hey, you're...
（タナベ）あっ さっきの…
（ハチマキ）またか
Not again...
どう？ 考えてくれた？
So, have you thought
it over?
いーや
I'll pass.
彼女の言うとおり―
Like she said just now, deciding what to leave
your loved ones is a difficult question, isn't it?
大切な人に何を残すかって
難しい問題よね
But with money they can convert it into all sorts of things, such as goods, but also
medical treatment or an education.
でも お金なら
品物は もちろん医療や教育等―
さまざまなものに
形を変えることができるわ
Um... I guess.
あっ いや まあ…
What will make a person happy
varies from person to person, right?
何に幸せを感じるかは
人それぞれよね
So don't you think the best thing is to leave it
up to the person who's going to use it?
使い道は使う人に任せるのが
一番だと思わない？
ま… まあな
Um... Sure.
That's not right at all!
そんなの違います！
You think so?
そうかしら？
Personally, I think
it's better than giving someone something they don't want and having it go to waste.
その人が望んでいないものを残して
無駄になるよりいいと思うけど
This isn't a question of
gaining or losing things!
損とか得とかの話じゃありません！
最後に残るのが お金なんて
さみしすぎるって言ってるんです
I'm saying that leaving money behind
when you die is too sad for words!
あら そう じゃあ あなたは
大切な人に何を残すつもり？
Oh, you think so? What do you plan
on leaving to your loved ones, then?
愛です！
I'll leave them love!
あっ？
（ハチマキ）愛？
Love...?
Hey! That's it!
I should leave behind love!
（タナベ）そうか そうですよ
愛を残せばいいんです！
保険も愛でいいじゃないですか
Love is insurance
enough, too!
さあ まあ
考え方は人それぞれだし…
I see.
Well, to each his own, I suppose.
また来るね 八郎太さん
考えといてねん
I'll see you again, Hachirota-san.
Think it over, okay?
ボーナス 出たらな
Maybe if I get
a bonus.
（タナベ）そうか 愛だったんだ
That's it... Love was the
answer all along...
お前って ある意味すげえな
Y'know, in a sense,
you're amazing.
はい？
What?
Or at least unpretentious.
いや 天然つうか
感心したよ ほんと
I was impressed, I have to tell you.
（チェンシン）アハハッ
愛を残すか 大物だね 彼女
She'll leave love, huh?
That girl is a real find.
一緒に仕事してないから
笑ってられるんだよ
You're only laughing 'cause you
don't have to work with her.
That girl is
seriously scary.
実際 怖いぜ あの女
でも 彼女の言うとおり―
I think she's right, though. You should put some
thought into it when you're writing your will.
遺言は
ちゃんと書いたほうがいいと思うよ
でもさ なんか違うんだよな
Maybe, but I sorta think
they're both wrong.
うん？
Money or words or whatever,
that's not what I want to leave when I'm gone.
金とか 言葉とかさ
残したいものって
そうじゃねえんだよ
じゃあ 何 残すんだって
聞かれたら―
But when somebody asks me what I'm gonna
leave behind, I don't have an answer...
分かんねえけどよ
（保険外交員１）ご安心ください
うちは業界ナンバーワンですから
Rest assured, sir! We're rated
number one in the industry!
（保険外交員２）お願いしますよ
今日中にノルマをこなさないと
I'm begging you! If I don't meet
my quota this month, they'll... Chief?
課長さん 課長さーん
Chief!
（課長）我慢 我慢
この時期さえ乗り切れば
Hang in there... Hang in there... I just need
to make it through this one last season.
（ラビィ）課長
Remember, Chief, I was the one
who came up with this nice little plan.
このナイスな作戦を考えたのは
私ですからね
（エーデル）課長補佐
Chief, this paperwork
is all right, isn't it?
この書類は
これでいいんですよね？
（課長）これで
余計な保険に入ることもない
This way, I won't sign up for
insurance that I don't need!
（エーデル）課長補佐
（ラビィ）定年退職したとき―
Chief?
Recommend me as your replacement
once you retire, okay?
後釜には
このラビィを推薦してくださいよ
（エーデル）
係長補佐でもいいんですけど
You can check this, too, Manager.
（課長とラビィの笑い声）
（エーデル）働けよ
Do some work,
damn it...
（タナベ）先輩
遺言状のことなんですけど
Senpai, about that will...
（ハチマキ）
ああっ お前もしつけえなあ
Crap, you're persistent!
（タナベ）先輩の分ですって
I mean yours!
私 考えたんですけど―
I've been thinking, and, well,
does a last will have to be words?
遺言状って 文字じゃなくても
いいんじゃないですか？
あっ…
Why do you think I drew a picture?
（ハチマキ）
だから 絵を描いたじゃないか
No, what about a movie letter
or something?
（タナベ）そうじゃなくて
ムービーレターとか どうですか？
文字だと構えちゃうけど
ムービーだったら―
With words, you sound formal,
but with a movie letter,
...you could be lighthearted about it,
like you were calling your mom or dad.
お父さんやお母さんに
電話する気分で 気軽に…
I can't do that!
I can't call my old man!
（ハチマキ）できるわけねえだろ！
親父(おやじ)に電話なんて
（タナベ）えっ あっ…
すいません 私 知らなくて
I'm sorry, I didn't know...
Nah, he's alive.
Alive, kicking, and then some.
（ハチマキ）
生きてるって ピンピンしてるよ
Did you have a falling out? Shouldn't you have
outgrown your rebellious phase by now?
（タナベ）仲 悪いんですか？
反抗期にしても長すぎでしょ？
お父さんに心配かけちゃ…
（ハチマキ）うるせえ！
You shouldn't make
your father worry...
Shut up!
ただの仕事仲間が
家(うち)の中まで口出しすんな！
A stupid coworker doesn't have any right
to butt into my family life!
うっとうしいんだよ
いちいち お前は
You're getting on my damn nerves
with all your nagging!
（タナベ）あっ…
（ハチマキ）ユーリ やっぱり
手伝ってもらって よかったよ
Yuri, I'm glad we had you
come out here to help.
新人と２人でやるには多すぎる
There's too much to handle
with just me and the rookie.
Guys, could I talk you
into some overtime?
急で悪いんだけど
拾ってもらいたいデブリがあるの
Sorry for the short notice, but there's a piece
of debris that I want you to pick up.
短周期のすい星軌道を
飛んでたやつが―
Looks like something that was on a short-period cometary orbit got grabbed by Earth's gravity.
地球の引力に
つかまっちゃったらしいのよ
I bet it's just scrap metal
or something, but still...
まあ 鉄くずか何かだと思うけど
（ハチマキ）俺たち
いっぱい拾ったとこなんだけど
We've already got a pretty
big haul as it is...
They say there's a research agency that wants it.
Plus, you're already in the neighborhood.
欲しがってる
研究機関があるんだって
あんたたちのすぐ近くだから
（ハチマキ）えーっ
文句 言わない研究には…
Save the complaints.
It's for research, so...
文句 言わない研究には…
（電子音）
うん？ 何？ これ
What is that?
Preparedness is peace of mind!
Satisfaction once you're signed up!
（保険外交員１）
備えて安心 入って満足
Accidents are covered, of course,
as are you're family's...
（保険外交員２）
事故はもちろん家族まで
Three months, that's all I ask!
（保険外交員３）
３か月だけでいいから！
We're rated number one in the industry!
Our company offers
300% peace of mind!
（保険外交員５）
安心 300パーセント 我が社に
（保険外交員６）どうでしょう
目を通していただくだけでも
Please, just look it over...
（保険外交員７）
お嬢さん どこか決められました？
Hello there, Miss! Have you settled
on an insurance company yet?
私は派遣社員ですので
No, I'm a temp worker.
そうですか
Oh, is that so? Well, I'll leave a
pamphlet on the desk just in case.
じゃ 机の上に
パンフだけ置いておきますね
要らないっつうの
I don't need any, you jerk.
申し訳ありません 課長
私は 一足先に避難させて…
I'm sorry, Chief, but I'm
abandoning ship...
あっ…
（女性）いかがでしょう
お子さんの将来も考えてみては
How about it? Shouldn't you
think of your children's future?
Our tuition plan was put together
with exactly that in mind!
そのためだけに用意された
我が社の学費プラン お得ですよ
It's a bargain.
もう 何言うのよ まったく
How many of you people
are there?
やっぱりか
Just as I thought...
（タナベ）何なんですか？ それ
What is that thing?
Take a look.
（ハチマキ）ほらよ
えっ…
えっ うわっ そ… それは！
I-lt's a...
おいおい なんて面だい
笑ってやんの
Holy crap, would you look
at that expression?
He's smiling.
Is that seriously a...
（タナベ）それって もしかして…
A coffin from
a space burial.
宇宙葬の棺おけですよ
ここに書いてあります
It's written right here.
"Astronaut lbn Fadlan."
“航宙士 イブン･ファドラン”
"In accordance with his final wishes,
he set sail into the infinite sea. 2024."
“遺言により
無限の海に船出す 2024年”
宇宙葬 廃止直前ですね
That was right before space
burials were banned.
It's a corpse from
more than 50 years ago.
50年以上前の仏さんだ
He must've been launched on a heading
to leave the solar system,
太陽系外に向けて
射出されたんだろうが―
戻ってきちまったんだな
...but it looks like
he came back.
はあ…
He must've wanted to reach
the edge of the universe,
（ハチマキ）宇宙の果てまで
行きたかったんだろうが―
...but he couldn't
break free of gravity.
重力を振り切れなかったんだ
The odds against this are incredible.
It's damn near a miracle.
でも すげえ確率
ほとんど奇跡だよ
あの軌道じゃ
次に地球とランデブーするのは―
On that orbit, his next rendezvous with Earth
wouldn't have been for another 700 years.
700年後だもんな
What's going to be done
with the body?
あの遺体 どうなるんですか？
Don't know, don't care.
知らねえよ そんなの
Our job's to collect debris,
end of story.
俺たちの仕事は
デブリを回収するだけだしさ
What do you mean, debris?
That's a person's body!
デブリって 遺体ですよ
宇宙に浮かんでる不必要な物体は
デブリに決まってるだろ？
Any useless object floating around
in space is debris, you know?
How can you be
so coldhearted?
（タナベ）
さみしいこと 言わないでください
あれは人の生きてきた証しです！
（ハチマキ）うっ… わあっ
It's proof that he
was alive once!
信じられない 物扱いするなんて
You're unbelievable,
treating that man like a thing!
お前な 仕事だって
何回 言ったら分かるんだよ
How many times am I gonna have to spell out
your job description before it sinks in?
ご苦労さん みんな
Good work, everyone.
フィーさん
あの遺体 どうなるんですか？
Fee-san, what's gonna happen
to that body?
今 管制課が
遺族と連絡を取ってる
Control Section is contacting
his next of kin as we speak.
法律上 遺体の所有権は
遺族にあるんだって
They said that legally speaking, the body
is the property of the next of kin.
This is Seven Delivery.
You are cleared for flight to Baikonur...
（管制官）
こちら セブンデリバリー…
You're certain that
it's my father?
（ファドランの娘）
本当に父なんですか？
（クレア）
ええ 大変 珍しいケースです
Yes, ma'am. This is
a most unusual case.
2028年以前に行われた
宇宙葬に関しては―
As far as burials conducted
prior to 2028 are concerned,
...you would be able to re-bury him
as a special exception.
特例として
やり直しもできますが？
（ファドランの娘）あの…
Um...
（クレア）はい
Ma'am?
回収された方と話せますか？
Would it be possible for me to speak
with the people who recovered him?
ファドラン航宙士の娘さん？
Astronaut Fadlan's daughter?
（クレア）ええ 直接 そちらと
話したいということなので―
Yes. She says she'd like to speak with you face
to face, so I'm going to patch her through.
回線をつなぎます ユ ーコピー？
You copy?
I copy.
ファドラン航宙士を回収した
DS-12の船長―
I'm Fee Carmichael, captain of the DS-12, the
ship that recovered Astronaut Fadlan's body.
フィー･カーマイケルです
Um... This is an awkward question,
but how did my father's body look?
その…
つかぬことをお聞きしますが―
父の遺体は どんな様子でした？
（フィー）え？
I'm ashamed to say it, but I
never looked at my father's body.
（ファドランの娘）
恥ずかしながら―
私 父の遺体を
確認していないんです
ああ…
He was smiling.
He must've had a full life.
笑ってたよ 仏さん
満足な人生だったんだろうな
あっ…
そうですか
I see.
Is something
the matter?
あの… 何か？
（ファドランの娘）父は…
私の父は純粋な宇宙飛行士でした
Father... My father was an astronaut
through and through.
スペースプレーンの
パイロットという仕事を―
He was extremely proud of his work
as the pilot of a spaceplane,
とても誇りにしていて―
私たちが待っている
家に帰ってくることは―
...and he seldom returned to the home
where we were waiting for him.
ほとんどなく…
しかし 宇宙放射線で
体を悪くし―
But he grew sick
from cosmic radiation,
引退して間もなく
息を引き取りました
...and soon after he retired,
he passed away.
“地球で死にたくない”と
言い残して…
He stated in his will that he
didn't want to be buried on Earth.
私 怖かったんですね
父の顔を見るのが
I suppose I was afraid
to look at my father's face.
宇宙葬をしてしまったら
もう 本当に会えなくなるのに―
I knew that once we held the space burial,
I would never be able to see him again,
どんな顔しているんだろうと
考えたら…
...but when I wondered to myself what sort
of expression he had on his face, I...
現に 遺言状に―
The truth is, my mother and I were not
mentioned at all in his will.
私と母のことなど
ひと言も書かれていませんでしたし
いつも遠い目をしている人で―
He was a man whose eyes
were always on the horizon,
私を見ていても
目の焦点は私を通り越していました
...and even when he did look at me, they were
always focused on a point far beyond me.
父の目の焦点は いつも
深宇宙で結ばれていたのです
Father's eyes were always
locked on deep space.
Is that true...?
So, Father was smiling, was he?
そうですか
笑っていましたか 父は
父は…
父を宇宙に返してやってください
Father... Please send Father
back into space.
分かりました では こちらで
宇宙葬をやり直します
I understand. In that case,
we'll see to re-burying him ourselves.
よろしく お願いします
Thank you for all
your trouble.
それが父の本望でしょうから
I think this is what my father
would have wanted.
No, you can't do that!
駄目ですよ そんなの
何言っちゃってるんですか？
What are you saying?!
（フィー）ちょ…
落ち着きなさい タナベ
Calm down, Tanabe!
You can't send your father
back into space!
お父さんを
宇宙に返しちゃいけません
家族なら一緒にいなくちゃ
You're his family,
so he should be with you!
おい 新入り
昨日今日 宇宙に出たばっかで―
Hey, rookie, you haven't been in space that long,
so don't start talking like you own the place!
勝手なこと抜かしてんじゃ…
んんん…
お父さんは大事でしょう？
Your father's precious to you,
isn't he?
そんなの宇宙だろうが
地球だろうが 一緒です！
Whether he's in Earth or space,
that doesn't change!
タナベ！
Tanabe!
Aw, just let
that little twerp go.
放っとけ あんなやつ
What she says does make
some sense, though.
しかし
彼女の言うことにも一理ある
ああ？
（タナベ）ったく もう…
Unbelievable... What is it with astronauts
and trying to act tough?!
宇宙飛行士ってやつは
カッコばっかりつけて
では 当社で搬送し―
All right, then. Our company
will ship him to the moon,
月面上のマスドライバーで
太陽系外へ射出します
...where we'll fire him towards extra-solar space
using the mass driver there.
よろしいですね？
Is that all right?
はい それで結構です
Yes, that's fine.
（フィー）分かりました
Very well, then.
ハチ 墓場軌道に向かうよ
Hachi, we're heading for the graveyard orbit.
Pass word to Tanabe.
タナベにも伝えて
（ハチマキ）ああ
Sure. Hey, rookie! How long
are you gonna keep sulking?
おい 新入り
（警告音）
いつまで すねてんだよ
（フィー）ん？
（警告音）
ああっ！
（ハチマキ）どうした？
What's wrong?
あのバカ コンテナを
That little idiot opened
the cargo container!
（ハチマキ）
何 考えてんだ？ 新入りのやつ
What the hell
is that rookie thinking?
いっぺん 締めて―
We're gonna have to wring her neck
to let her know who's boss around here.
上下関係ってもんを
教えてやらねえとな
（フィー）タナベ
戻ってきなさい タナベ
Tanabe, come back! Tanabe!
Damn it, girl,
answer me!
返事ぐらいしろってんだよ！
戻ってこいっつってんだろうが
ああ？
Get your ass back
in here, damn it!
（ハチマキ）こら！
何しようとしてんだ？ 新入り
Hey!
What are you trying
to pull, rookie?!
Don't come near me!
来ないでください！
If you come any closer, I'll chuck
this thing into the atmosphere!
それ以上 近づくと
大気圏にぶん投げますよ これ
（ハチマキ）えっ…
な… 何言ってんだよ おい
W-What are you saying?
本気ですからね
I'm serious!
Um...
えーっと…
お前 バカだ 底なしだ
You're an idiot.
A bottomless pit of stupidity.
そんなことに
何の意味があんだよ
What good is that
gonna do?
Look at that will you wrote!
You're the one with the problem!
先輩なんて―
あんな遺言状 書いてるから
いけないんですよ
どうして 分からないんですか？
Why can't you understand?!
We can't send this man back into space!
この人は
宇宙に返しちゃ駄目なんです！
（ハチマキ）そんなの
お前が決めることじゃねえだろ
That's not up to you
to decide!
That man wanted
to be buried in space!
その仏さんは
宇宙で死にたかったんだ
As a fellow astronaut,
I understand how he feels.
同じ宇宙飛行士として
その気持ちは分かる
Let's give him
what he wants!
そうさせてやろうぜ
違います！
ファドランさんは後悔してたんです
You're wrong! Mr. Fadlan
regretted his decision!
宇宙をさまよって やっぱり
戻ってきたいと思ったんですよ
He was drifting in space and he
said to himself, "I want to go back!"
どうして
そんなことが言えるんだ！
How can you say that?!
Don't ignore the man's wishes
and force your own dreams on him!
本人 無視して
自分勝手な夢 見てんじゃねえよ
でも… でも ファドランさんは
帰ってきたんですよ
But Mr. Fadlan came back!
Against astronomical odds!
天文学的な確率で
先輩も奇跡だって
You yourself said
it was a miracle!
奇跡って お前…
A miracle?
What are you...
And why do you suppose
that miracle happened?
（タナベ）どうして
奇跡が起きたんだと思います？
それは ファドランさんが
そう願ったからです
Because Mr. Fadlan
wished for it!
奇跡を起こすくらい
強く願ったからです
He wanted it so bad that
it made a miracle happen!
He said, "I want to go back to Earth!
I want to go back to my family!"
地球に戻りたい
家族のところに行きたいって！
違う！ ただの偶然だ
You're wrong!
It was just a coincidence!
（タナベ）奇跡です！
It was a miracle!
先輩こそ 自分に都合よく
言わないでくださいよ
Don't you go saying what
you want to hear, Senpai!
（ハチマキ）なんでだよ
Why are you doing this?! It was his
own choice to live alone and die alone!
そのおっさんは 一人で生きて
一人で死ぬって決めたんだ
And it was
the wrong decision!
絶対に違います！
だって ファドランさんは
愛されてるじゃないですか
For one thing, Fadlan-sama is loved by people, isn't he?!
By his wife, his daughter, and I bet
even his parents and friends, too!
奥さんや 娘さんや
きっと 両親や友達にも
そういう人が自分勝手なことして
宇宙のかなたで―
A man like that can't be selfish and decide to
turn into a mummy at the ends of the universe!
冷凍ミイラに
なったりしちゃ駄目です！
地球に戻るべきなんです
それが愛じゃないんですか？
He should go back to Earth!
Isn't that what love's all about?
私なら 死んでも
大切な人のところに戻ってきますよ
If it were me, I'd want to go back and be
with my loved ones, even if I was dead!
Living alone
and dying alone...
１人で生きて １人で死んで
１人で…
Alone...
なんで満足できるんですか？
バカみたい
How could anyone
be satisfied with that?
It's stupid...
宇宙は
１人きりじゃ広すぎるのに…
Space is too big
to face all alone.
（ファドランの娘）
あの… 船長さん
Um... Captain?
ん？
（フィー）
棺おけ 下ろしなさい タナベ
Put the coffin down, Tanabe. His daughter
says she wants to claim the body.
娘さんが遺体を引き取りたいって
はっ…
くっ…
What?
（タナベ）ええっ…
But I've already sent the forms
over to Welfare Section...
でも 手続きはこちらだって
福祉課に…
はい 分かりました
Yes, sir, I understand.
（ユーリ）どうしたんです？
What's the matter?
遺体を地球に下ろす手続きって
いろいろ面倒なのよ
There's a lot of hoops to jump through
to send a body back to Earth.
でも あそこまで言ったからには
やってもらわないといけませんね
Still, after all those things she said,
she has to be the one to deal with it.
The written report?
I'm submitting it to INTO, so...
報告書？ 連合に提出するので…
書式が違う？
It's not written properly?
確か 前のに…
Hang on...
It was around here...
うわあ！
ご契約 ありがとうございました
Thank you so much
for the contracts!
（課長）ごめんよ 母ちゃん
Forgive me, Mother...!
（ラビィ）教育ローンが…
What do I need with
a student loan?!
あら？
Hm?
よう 契約まとまったみたいだな
Hey. Looks like you
got your contracts.
あなたとは まだでしょ？
これなんか どう？
I still haven't got one from you, though.
How about this, then?
It's our top of the line item.
The "Double Plan for Lovers."
我が社のイチオシ商品
愛情ダブルプラン
ケッ！ 何が愛だよ
（女性）え？
"Love," my ass...
俺は認めないぞ
I don't buy it.
宇宙がそんなに甘くて
たまるかってんだよ
No way in hell is the universe
that sentimental!
♪～
♪グッと水を飲み干し
gutto mizu wo nomihoshi
We gulp down some water
yuuyakegumo miageru no sa
and look up at the evening clouds.
♪夕焼け雲見上げるのさ
♪今日も一日が終わって
kyou mo ichinichi ga owatte
Let's wind our way home under the roadside trees as another day ends.
♪街路樹の下を帰ろう
gairoju no shita wo kaerou
yaru koto darake de tenpatte
Even if life's so hectic that our tempers flare,
♪やることだらけで
テンパって、
♪無理をして、
つまずいても
muri wo shite tsumazuite mo
we push ourselves too hard, and we stumble,
♪何か必ず
つかんでるさ
nani ka kanarazu tsukanderu sa
I know there'll be something to grab hold of.
♪気楽にいこうぜ
kiraku ni ikou ze
Let's move on without a care in our hearts.
♪素晴らしい人生だから
subarashii jinsei dakara
It's a wonderful life.
♪自分を愛する
勇気を持とう
jibun wo aisuru yuuki wo motou
So let's have the courage to love ourselves.
♪新しいドア叩いて
atarashii doa tataite
Let's take it one step at a time,
♪ひとつひとつ
歩いてゆこう
hitotsu hitotsu aruite yukou
knocking on new doors on the way.
♪素晴らしい人生なのさ
subarashii jinsei na no sa
It's a wonderful life.
♪君も僕もすべての人も
kimi mo boku mo subete no hito mo
You and I and everyone else
♪喜びと悲しみの意味
yorokobi to kanashimi no imi
Keep on searching for the meaning
♪探しつづけて
so just on my way
sagashitsuzukete so just on my way
Of joy and sadness, so just on my way.
Next Time
Part of the Job
その新入りっての―
Could you please stop
with that "rookie" stuff?
いいかげん
やめてください
（コリン）
僕 コリン･クリフォード
I'm Colin Clifford.
Maybe you've heard of me.
知ってるかな？
（ハチマキ）あっ…
Why does it have to be us?
Go make the PR Section do it!
なんで俺たちなんだよ
そういうのは
広報課にでも言えよな
We're doing this
to help you.
あなたたちのために
やってるのよ
ああ？
That way, your parents would never know
that you collect garbage in space.
宇宙でゴミ拾いなんて―
親にも
ないしょだったりして
You do the same pathetic job,
day in and day out.
毎日 毎日―
くだんない仕事を
ちまちまとさ
デブリ屋は
最高にカッコいいです
Debris collectors are
as cool as they come!